hi this is the first lecture in MIT s
course 1806 linear algebra and I'm
Gilbert Strang the text for the course
is this book introduction to linear
algebra and the course web page which
has got a lot of exercises from the past
MATLAB codes the syllabus for the course
is web dot mit.edu slash 18 point oh six
and this is the first lecture lecture
one so and later we'll say where which
will give the web address for viewing
these videotapes okay so what's in the
first lecture this is my plan the
fundamental problem of linear algebra
which is to solve a system of linear
equations so let's start with the case
when we have some number of equations
say n equations and n unknowns so an
equal number of equations and unknowns
that's the normal nice case and what I
want to do is with examples of course to
describe first what I call the role
picture that's the picture of one
equation at a time it's the picture
you've seen before in two by two
equations where lines meet so in a
minute you'll see lines meeting the
second picture well I put a star beside
that because that's such an important
one and may be new to you is the picture
a column at a time and those are the
rows and columns of a matrix so the
third the algebra way to look at the
problem is the matrix form in
using a matrix that I'll call a okay so
can I do an example the whole semester
we'll be examples and then see what's
going on with it with the example so
take an example two equations two
unknowns so let me take 2x minus y
equals 0 let's say and minus X plus say
2 y equals 3 okay look I can even say
right away what's the matrix that that
is what's the coefficient matrix the
matrix that involves these numbers a
matrix is just a rectangular array of
numbers here the here it's 2 rows and 2
columns so 2 and minus 1 in the first
row minus 1 and 2 in the second row
that's the matrix and the right-hand the
unknown well we've got two unknowns so
we've got a vector X with two components
x and y and we've got two right-hand
sides that go into a vector 0 3
I couldn't resist writing the matrix
form right or even before the before the
pictures so I always will think of this
as the matrix a the matrix of
coefficients then there's a vector of
unknowns here we've only got two
unknowns later we'll have any number of
unknowns and that vector of unknowns
well I'll often I'll make that X extra
extra bold and the right-hand side is
also a vector that I'll always call B so
linear equations are ax equal B and the
idea now is to solve this particular
example and then step back to see the
bigger picture okay what's the picture
for this example the row
picture ok so here comes the role
picture so that means I take one row at
a time and I'm drawing here the XY plane
and I'm gonna put plot all the points
that satisfy that first equation so I'm
looking at all the points that satisfied
2x minus y equals 0 I'm often it's often
good to start with which point on the
horizontal line on this horizontal line
y is 0 the x axis has Y is 0 and that in
this case actually then X is 0 so the
point the origin the point with
coordinates 0 0 is on the line
it solves that equation ok tell me and I
guess I have to tell you another point
that solves this same equation let me
suppose X is 1 so I'll take X to be 1
then Y should be 2 right so there's the
point 1 2 that also solves this equation
then I could put in more points by that
but let me put in all the points at once
because they all lie on a straight line
this is a linear equation and that word
linear we've got the letters for line in
it that's the equation that's this is
the line that of the of solutions to 2x
minus y equals 0 my first row first
equation so typically may be X equal 1/2
y equal 1 will work and it's sure enough
it does ok that's the first one now the
second one is not going to go through
the origin it's always the important do
we go through the origin or not in this
case yes because there's a 0 over there
in this case we don't go through the
origin because if x and y are 0 we don't
get 3 so
let me again say suppose Y is zero what
X do we actually get if Y is 0 then I
get X is minus 3 so if Y is 0 I go along
minus 3 so there's one point on this
second line now let me say well suppose
X is minus 1 just to take another X if X
is minus 1 then this is a 1 and I think
Y should be a 1 because if X is minus 1
then I think why should be a 1 and we'll
get that point is that right if X is
minus 1 that's a 1 if Y is a 1 that's a
2 and the 1 and the 2 make 3 and that
points on the equation ok now I should
just draw the line right connecting
those two points that that will give me
the whole line and if I've done this
reasonably well I think it's going to
happen to go through well not happen it
was arranged to go through that point so
I think that the second line is this one
and this is the all-important point that
lies on both lines so we just checked at
that point which which is the point X
equal 1 and Y was two right that's the
point there and that I believe solves
both equations let's just check this if
X is 1 I have a minus 1 plus 4 equals 3
ok apologies for drawing this picture
that you've seen before but this seeing
the row picture first of all for n equal
to 2 equations in two unknowns it's the
right place to start
ok so we've got the solution the point
that lies on both lines now can I come
to the column picture pay attention this
is the key point
so the column picture I'm now going to
look at the columns of the matrix I'm
going to look at this part and this part
I'm going to say that the the X part is
really so so is really x times you see
I'm putting the two I'm kind of getting
the two equations at once that part and
then I have a y and and in the first
equation its multiplying a minus one and
in second equation a 2 and on the right
hand side 0 and 3 you see the columns of
the matrix the columns of a are here and
the right-hand side B is there and now
what is the equation asking for it's
asking us to find some how to combine
that vector and this one in the right
amounts to get that one it's asking us
to find the right linear combination
this is called a linear combination and
it's the most fundamental operation in
the whole course it's a linear
combination of the columns that's what
we're seeing on the left side again I
don't want to write down a big
definition you can see what it is
there's column one there's column two I
multiplied by some numbers and I add
that's a combination a linear
combination and I want to make those
numbers the right numbers to produce
zero three okay
now I want to draw a picture that
represents what this this is algebra
what's the geometry what's the picture
that goes with it
okay so again these vectors have two
components so I better draw a picture
like that so can I put down these
columns I'll draw these columns as they
are and then I'll do do a combination of
them so the first column
is over 2 and down 1 right so there's
the first column the first column column
1 it's the vector 2 minus 1 the second
column is C I go over minus 1 is the
first component and up to its here
there's column 2 so this again you see
what its components are its components
are minus 1 2 good
that's this guy now what is what now I
have to take a combination what
combination shall I take
why not the right combination what the
hell okay so what the combination I'm
going to take is the right one to
produce 0 3 and that and then we'll see
it happen in the picture so the right
combination is to take X is one of those
and two of these it's because we already
know that that's the right x and y so
why not take the correct combination
here and see it happen okay so how do I
picture this this linear combination so
I start with this vector that's already
here so that's one of column 1 that's 1
times column 1 right there and now I
want to add on so I'm going to hook the
next vector on to the front of the arrow
we'll start the next vector and it'll go
this way so let's see can I do it right
if I add it on one of these vectors it
would go left one and up two so it would
go left one and up two so it would
probably get us two there maybe I'll do
dotted line for that ok that's one of
column to tuck down to the end but I
wanted to talk on two of column 2 so
that the second one will go up like left
1 and up 2 also it'll probably end there
and there's another one so so what I've
put in here is 2
of column 2 added on and where did I end
up what are the coordinates of this
result what do I get when I take one of
this plus two of that I do get that of
course there it is there it is X is zero
Y is three that's B that's the that's
the answer we wanted and how do I do it
you see I do it just like the first
component I have a two and a and a minus
two that produces a zero and in the
second component I have a minus one and
a four they combine to give the three
but look at this picture so that here's
our key picture I combine this column
and this column to get maybe I better to
get this guy that was the B that's the
zero three okay
so that idea of linear combinations is
crucial and and also do we want to think
about this question sure why not what
are all the combinations if I took can I
go back to X's and Y's this is a this is
a question for really it's it's going to
come up over and over but why don't we
see it once now if I took all the X's
and all the Y's all the combinations
what would be all the results and
actually the result would be that I
could get any right-hand side at all the
combinations of this and this would fill
the whole plane you can tuck that away
we'll just explore it further but this
idea of what linear combination gives B
and what do all the linear combinations
give what are all the possible
achievable right-hand side
be that's gonna be basic okay can I move
to three equations and three unknowns
because it's easy to picture the two by
two case let me do a three by three
example okay I'll sort of start it the
same way say maybe 2x minus y and maybe
I'll take no no Z's is a zero and maybe
a minus X and a 2y and maybe a minus Z
is a oh let me make that a minus one and
just for variety let me take minus 3z
2-3 wise I should keep the Y's in that
line and for Z's is safe for okay that's
three equations I'm in three dimensions
XYZ and I don't have a solution yet so I
want to understand the equations and
then solve them okay so how do i how do
you understand them the row picture is
one way the column picture is another
very important way just let's remember
the matrix form here cuz that's easy the
matrix form
what's our matrix a our matrix a is this
right hand side the 2 and the minus 1
and the 0 from the first row the minus 1
and the 2 and the minus 1 from the
second row the 0 the minus 3 and the 4
from the third row so it's a three by
three matrix three equations three
unknowns and what's our right hand side
of course it's the vector 0 minus 1/4
okay so that's the way we'll that's the
shorthand to write out the three
equations but it's the picture that I'm
looking for today okay
so the row picture
all right so I'm in three dimensions X Y
& Z and I want to take those equations
one at a time and ask and make a picture
of all the points that satisfy let's
take equation number two if I make a
picture of all the points and satisfy
all the XYZ points that solve this
equation well first of all the origin is
not one of them
XYZ it being zero zero zero would not
solve that equation so what what are
some points that do solve the equation
let's see maybe if X is one y + Z could
be zero that would work right so there's
one point I'm looking at this second
equation here just to start with let's
see also I guess if Z Z could be 1x and
Y could be zero so that would just go
straight up that axis and probably I
want a third point here let me take X to
be zero let's say X to be zero Z to be
zero then Y would be minus 1/2 right so
there's a third point somewhere oh my
okay let's see I want to put in all the
points that satisfy that equation do you
know what that bunch of points will be
it's a plane if we have a linear
equation then fortunately the graph of
the thing the plot of all the points
that solve it or a plane so I and three
these three points determine a plane but
your lecture is not Rembrandt and this
the art is going to be the weak point
here so I'm just going to draw a plane
right there's a plane somewhere that's
my plane the
that that that plane is all the points
it solves this guy then what about this
one
2x minus y plus zero Z so Z actually can
be anything again it's going to be
another plane each row in a 3x3 problem
gives us a plane in three dimensions so
this one is going to be some other plane
maybe it maybe I'll try to draw it like
this and those two planes meet in a line
so if I have two equations just the
first two equations in in three
dimensions those give me a line the line
where those two planes meet and now the
third guy is a third plane and it goes
some somewhere ok those three things
meet at a point now I don't know where
that point is frankly but linear algebra
will find it main point is that there is
that the three planes because they're
you know they're not parallel they don't
they're not special there they do meet
in one point and that's the solution but
maybe you can see that this row picture
is getting a little hard to see the road
picture was a cinch when we looked at to
me two lines meeting when we look at
three planes meeting it's not so clear
and in four dimensions probably a little
less clear
so can I quit on the row picture I'll
quit on the row picture before I've
successfully found the point where the
three planes meet all I really want to
see is that there that the row picture
consists of three planes and if
everything works right three planes meet
in one point and that's a solution now
you can tell I prefer the column picture
okay so let me take the column picture
that's x times so there were two x's in
the first equation minus one X is I'm
just take and no X is in the third it's
just the first column of that and how
many Y's are there there's minus one in
the first equation two in the second and
maybe minus three in the third just the
second column of my matrix and Z times
no Z's - onesies and for Z's and it's
those three columns right that I have to
combine to produce the right-hand side
which is 0 minus 1/4
okay so what have we got on this
left-hand side a linear combination it's
a linear combination now of three
vectors and they happen to be each one
is a 3-dimensional vector so we want to
but we want to know what combination of
those three vectors produces that one
shall I try to draw the column picture
then so since these vectors have three
components so it's some multiple let me
draw in the first column as before so I
X is 2 and Y is minus 1 maybe maybe
there's the first column Y the second
column has maybe a minus 1 and a 2 and
the Y's and minus 3 some somewhere there
possibly column 2 and the third column
has no no 0 minus 1/4 so how shall I
draw that so nothing in this is this was
that this is the first component the
second component was a minus 1 maybe up
here that's column 3 that's that's the
column 0 minus 1 and for this guy so
again what's my problem
my what this equation is asking me to do
is to combine these three vectors with
the right combination to produce this
one well you can see what the right
combination is because in this special
problem especially chosen by the
lecturer that right hand side that I'm
trying to get is actually one of these
columns so I know how to get that one so
what's the solution what combination
will work I just want one of these and
none of these so X should be 0 y should
be 0 and Z should be one they come
that's the combination none of that none
of that one of those is obviously the
right one so this column 3 is actually
the same as B in this particular problem
I made it work that way just so we would
get an answer 0 0 1 so somehow that's
the point that where those three planes
met and I couldn't see it before of
course I won't always be able to see it
from the column picture either it's the
next lecture actually which is about
elimination which is the systematic way
that everybody every every bit of
software to production large-scale
software would solve the equations so
that the lecture that's coming up if I
was to add that to the syllabus will be
about how to find X Y Z in in all cases
can I just think again though about the
big picture the big buy the big picture
I mean let's keep this same matrix on
the left but imagine that we have a
different right-hand side oh let me take
a different right-hand side so
change that right hand side to something
that actually is also pretty special let
me change it to suppose I if I add those
first two columns that would give me a 1
and a 1 and a minus 3 there's a very
special right hand side I just cooked it
up by adding this one to this one now
what's the solution with this new
right-hand side the solution with this
new right-hand side is clear it took now
I took one of these one of these and
none of those so so actually it just
changed around on this when I took this
new right-hand side okay so the in there
in the role picture I have three
different planes three three three new
planes meeting now at this point in the
column picture I have the same three
columns but now I'm combining them to
produce this guy and it turned out that
column one plus column two which would
be somewhere there there is the right
column one of this and one of this would
give me the the new B okay so that's
like we squeezed in an extra example but
now think about all B's all right hand
sides could I get can I solve these
equations for every right-hand side can
I say that asset question so that's the
algebra question can I solve ax equal B
for every B let me write that down
can I solve ax equal B for every
right-hand side B I mean is there a
solution and then if there is
elimination will give me a way to find
it I'm just I really wanted to ask is
there a solution for every right-hand
side so now can I put that in different
words in this linear
combination words so in linear
combination words do the linear
combinations of the columns fill
three-dimensional space every B means
all the B's in three-dimensional space
so machine that I'm just asking the same
question in in different words solving a
ax
oh that's very important a times X when
I multiply a matrix by a vector I get a
combination of the columns I'll write
that and get down in a moment
so that you see but in my column picture
that's really what I'm doing I'm taking
linear combinations of these three
columns and I'm trying to find B and
actually the answer for this matrix will
be yes for this matrix for this for this
matrix a for these columns the answer is
yes this matrix is this this this matrix
that that I chose for an example is a
good matrix a non singular matrix an
invertible matrix so those will be the
matrices that we like best there could
be other and we will see other matrices
where the answer becomes no oh actually
you can see when it would become no when
could what what could go wrong how could
it go wrong that out of these out of
three columns and all their combinations
when would I not be able to produce some
be off here when when could it go wrong
do you see that the combinations
supposed let me say when it goes wrong
if these three columns all lie in the
same plane then their combinations will
lie in that same plane so then we're in
trouble if the three columns of my
matrix if those three vectors happen to
lie in the same plane
for example if column 3 is just the sum
of column 1 and column 2 I would be in
trouble that would be a matrix a where
the answer would be no because the
combinations if column 3 is in the same
plane as column 1 and 2 I don't get
anything new from that all the
combinations are in the plane and the
only right-hand sides B that I could get
would be the ones in that plane so I
could solve it for some right-hand sides
when B is in the in the plane but most
right-hand sides would be out of the
plane and unreachable so that would be a
singular case the matrix would be not
invertible there would not be a solution
for every B the answer would become no
for that okay I don't know
so we take just a little shot at
thinking about nine dimensions imagine
that we have vectors with nine
components well it's gonna be hard to
visualize those I don't pretend to do it
but somehow pretend you do pretend we
have if if this was nine equations in
nine unknowns then we would have nine
columns and each one would be a vector
in nine dimensional space and we would
be looking at their linear combinations
so we will be having the linear
nations of nine vectors in nine
dimensional space and we would be trying
to find the combination that hit the
correct right hand side B and we might
also ask the question can we always do
it
can we get every right hand side B and
certainly it will depend on those nine
columns some sometimes the answer will
be yes if I pick the random matrix it
would be yes actually
if I use MATLAB and just use the random
command picked out a 9 by 9 matrix I
guarantee it would be good it would be
non-singular it would be invertible all
beautiful but if I choose those columns
so that they're not independent so that
they're there so that the the ninth
column is the same as the 8th column
then it contributes nothing new and
there would be right-hand sides B that I
couldn't get can you sort of think about
9 vectors in 9 dimensional space and
take their combinations that's really
the the central thought that that you
get kind of used to in linear algebra
even so you can't really visualize it
you sort of think you can after a while
those 9 columns and all their
combinations may very well fill out the
whole nine dimensional space but if the
ninth column happened to be the same as
the 8th column and gave nothing new then
probably what it would fill out would be
I hesitate even to say this it would be
a come a sort of claim an 8 dimensional
plane inside 9 dimensional space and
it's those 8 dimensional planes inside
nine dimensional space that we have to
work with eventually for now let's stay
with a nice case
where the matrices work we can get every
right-hand side B and here we see how to
do it with columns okay there was one
step that I realize which I realized I
was saying in words that I now want to
write in letters because I'm coming back
to the matrix form of the equation so
let me write it here the matrix form
about my equation of my of my system is
some matrix a times some vector X equals
some right-hand side B okay so this is a
multiplication a times X matrix times
vector and I just want to say how do you
multiply a matrix by a vector okay so
I'm just going to create a a matrix let
me take 2 5 1 3 and let me take a vector
X to be say 1 and 2 how do I multiply a
matrix by a vector and we'll just think
a little bit about matrix notation and
how to do that multiplication so let me
say how I multiply a matrix by a vector
actually there are two ways to do it let
me tell you my favorite way it's a it's
its columns again it's a column at a
time for me that matrix mode this matrix
multiplication says I take one of that
column and two of that column and add so
this is in my the way I would think of
it is one of the first column and two of
the second column and and let's just see
what we get so in the first component
I'm getting a 2 and a 10 I'm getting a
12 there and the second component I'm
giving a 1 and a 6 I'm getting a 7 so
that that matrix times that vector is 12
7 now you could do that in a
away you could do it a row at a time you
could do and you would get this 12 and
actually I pretty much did it here this
way too
I could take that row times my vector
this is this is all the time this is the
idea of a dot product this vector times
this vector 2 times 1 plus 5 times 2 is
the 12 this vector times this vector 1
times 1 plus 3 times 2 is the 7 so I can
do it by rows and in each row each row
times my X is what I'll later call a dot
product but I also like to see it by
columns I see this as a linear
combination of the column so here's my
point a times X is a combination of the
columns of a that's that's how I hope
you'll think of a times X when we need
it right now we've got with small ones
we can always do it in different ways
but later think of it that way ok so
that's the picture for a 2 by 2 system
and if the right-hand side B happened to
be 12 7 then of course the correct
solution would be 1 2 okay so let me
come back next time to a systematic way
using elimination to find the solution
if there is one to any a system of any
size and find out because the system
because eliminate eliminate Enphase find
out when there isn't a solution okay
thanks
you